A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Research, Public Education, Office Files of Marjorie Martus FA714
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Research, Public Education, Office Files of Marjorie Martus
1962-1968, 1971-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA714
3.08 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been transferred to the appropriate collections. Crossreference sheets located within the folders, denote the new locations of these items which are listed in the back of this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
Marjorie Martus, Ford Foundation Program Officer in the Division of Education and Research (E&R), was a member of the Foundation staff from 1958 until 1982.
During this period, she held the following positions:
• October 1977, Program Officer, Division of Education and Research • October 1968, Program Officer, PE (Public Education), Division of Education and Research • October 1967, Assistant Program Officer, Division of Education and Research • January 1967, Program Assistant, PE, Division of Education and Research • October 1965, Program Assistant, Education Program • January 1958, Research Assistant, Education Program
Marjorie Martus was born July 13, 1923. She received her B.A. degree in 1945 from Antioch College. She did additional course work at Columbia University, New York University, and the Bank Street College of Education.
Prior to Martus' career with the Ford Foundation, she held the following positions:
• 1945-1946, Office of War Information, Information Specialist • 1946-1948, U.S. Department of State, Divisional Assistant, Division of International Exchange of Persons • 1948-1954, United States Government, Technical Assistance Specialist; Economic Cooperation Administration, The Hague, The Netherlands • 1954-1955, Douglas Williams Associates, Office Manager; Interviewer • 1955-1956, Milliontex, Inc., Officer Manager • 1956-1957, Rockefeller Bros. Fund, Staff Assistant
Following her retirement from the Ford Foundation, Miss Martus was employed by the School of Education at Stanford University.
Scope and Contents
The Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982.
The seven boxes of correspondence and reports which constitute the Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus, document her activities and a number of those of the Education Program for the years 1962 to 1968; and from 1971 to 1975.
The papers include material related to Ford Foundation educational activities and projects; and correspondence with Foundation colleagues, and individuals in academic, grantee and other organizations.
The papers are broad in scope, but are rather disappointingly superficial, especially in light of Miss Martus' activity and reputation. It is recommended that the researcher consult the files of grants for which Miss Martus served as Responsible Program Officer, a list of which is included in the appendix to this register.
Arrangement
The Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus are divided into two series:
I. Correspondence Files, 1962-1968, 1971-1975 II. Subject Files, 1962-1968
Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Martus' office.
Ford Foundation
- Correspondence Files, 1962-1968, 1971-1975; I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence Files (1962-1968; 1971-1975), contains correspondence generated by Miss Martus during her years at the Foundation. The correspondence is divided into two subseries:
  A. Chronological Files, which are arranged in reverse calendar order; and
  B. Alphabetical Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent. Within each Alphabetical File folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order
  - Chronological Files, A
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13-20)
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25-36)
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 37-48)
    - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 49-56)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 57-60)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 61-72)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 73-84)
    - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 85-96)
    - 1965 (Box 5, Folder 97-108)
    - 1964 November - May (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - 1964 April - January (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - 1963 December - 1962 July (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Alphabetical Files, B
    - Chilman, C., 1970 June - February (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Deutsch, M., 1966 December - 1965 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Farmer, J., 1966 August - 1965 May (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Gray, S., 1972 June - 1971 October (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Guttentag, M., 1969 August - 1968 November (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Hobson, A., 1968 February - 1967 November (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Hovet, M., 1967 March - 1966 March (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Keeve, P., 1968 January - 1967 January (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Miller, D., 1966 April - 1965 October (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Mohan, B., 1968 February - 1967 December (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Nicholls, J., 1967 September - August (Box 6, Folder 122)
- Subject Files, 1962-1968; II
  Series II, Subject Files (1962-1968), consists of correspondence and other material as it relates to each topic. The files are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Arizona Laboratory, 1967 December - October (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School, 1966 June - April (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Carolinas and Virginia Regional Laboratory, 1968 July - 1967 November (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Child Development, 1965 January - 1964 December (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Dyslexia, 1967 June - 1964 September (Box 6, Folder 127-128)
  - Early Childhood Education - DRAFT Material, 1966-1965 (Box 6, Folder 129-134)
  - Freyburg Academy (Reading Research Institute), 1966 March - 1962 June (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Institute for Developmental Studies, 1968 June - 1966 September (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Language Consultants - BA-HA, 1967-1966 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Language Consultants - JO-SE, 1967-1966 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Language Development Study, 1968 April - 1967 January (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Lexington School for the Deaf, 1967 February - 1965 January (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - National Institute for Mental Health, 1968 August - 1964 December (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1969 January (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1969-1968 (Box 7, Folder 143-144)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1969 January - 1968 December (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1969 January - 1968 December (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Ohio State University Research Consortium, 1968 May - 1967 December (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Pre-School Television, 1968 April - 1967 April (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Publication Orders, 1968 June - 1966 October (Box 7, Folder 149-150)
  - System Development Corporation, 1968 January - 1964 September (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Team Teaching, 1966 April - 1964 October (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Research and Development Centers - United States, 1969 November - 1967 March (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - School Improvement Work Conference, San Francisco, January 3-7, 1967, 1967 January (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Social Science Research Council Conference, Chicago, February 7-9, 1966, 1966 February - 1965 June (Box 7, Folder 155)
- Appendix A: Marjorie Martus Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished Ford Foundation reports by Marjorie Martus were removed from the papers. They are listed in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Benjamin Franklin High School, 1966 June 23 (Report 10344)
  - The Community Resources Institute - Grant #70-446, 1973 December 14 (Report 10345)
  - Language and Education: Some Opportunities for Advancing Knowledge and Practice (Report 10346)
  - Material for a Think-Piece on Early Learning, 1966 December (Report 10371)
  - Notes on Social Studies Curriculum Work, n.d. (Report 10347)
  - Observations and Recommendations Concerning the Teaching of Reading in Atlanta Schools Serving Disadvantaged Children, 1965 February 19 (Report 10348)
  - Reading Disabilities and Special Education, 1966 June 3 (Report 10349)
  - [The Role of Television in Education], 1960 June 7 (Report 10350)
  - The Special Case of the Young Disadvantaged Child, 1964 October 7 (Report 10351)
  - U.K. Assignments for American ETV Personnel, 1962 July (Report 10352)
  - Visit to Bernard van Leer Foundation, The Hague, The Netherlands, 1972 September 22 (Report 10353)
  - Visit to Human Ecology Research Station (HERS), Cali, Colombia, May 10-11, 1973, 1973 August 28 (Report 5832)
- Appendix B: Other FF Reports Removed
  The following list of unpublished reports written by other FF staff and consultants were removed from the papers. They are listed alphabetically by author. For each author, the reports are arranged in alphabetical order. The number at the left, is the assigned accession number. They have been transferred to the Foundation's Archives collection of staff and consultant reports.
  - Conant, Theodore. Final Recommendations Concerning the National Program for the Use of Television in the Schools and Related Projects, 1963 September (Report 2628)
  - Coombs, Philip H. The Technical Fronteirs of Education, 1960 March (Report 10354)
  - Fantini, Mario. Inner Content vs. Academic Content in Public Schools, 1967 March (Report 784)
  - Ford Foundation. Discussion Paper: Early Childhood Education, 1965 May (Report 10355)
  - Ford Foundation. Early Childhood: Reassessment of a Critical Period, 1964 Fall (Report 10356)
  - Ford Foundation. Fact Sheets on Education Improvement Projects Pre-School Through Community College, 1968 January (Report 10357)
  - Ford Foundation. The Ford Foundation and Noncommercial Television, 1967 December (Report 2772)
  - Ford Foundation. Language and Education (Report 10358)
  - Ford Foundation. Language Development Study - Background Papers (Report 6070)
  - Ford Foundation. Private Secondary Schools: A Summary of Available Data, 1962 May (Report 10359)
  - Ford Foundation. Program-Directed Investments: A Wider View of Philanthropy, 1968 March (Report 1426)
  - Gotkin, Lassar. A Calendar Curriculum for Kindergarten Children fro Disadvantaged Backgrounds: The Application of the Discipline of Programed Instruction to a Classroom Curriculum, 1966 September (Report 10360)
  - Gotkin, Lassar. On the Contribution of Montessori Materials for the Early Education of Young Children from Disadvantaged Backgrounds (Report 10361)
  - Gotkin, Lassar. Pre-School Education of Children from Disadvantaged Backgrounds and the Relevance of Montessori, 1967 October (Report 10362)
  - Gruber, Ruth. Some Israel Techniques in the Urban Assimilation of New Immigrants; and their Relevance for New York and Developing Countries (Report 10363)
  - Lenrow, Peter. Strengthening Early Education: Collaboration in Problem Solving, 1969 January (Report 10364)
  - Levine, Louis. The School and the Disadvantaged Community: The Dimension of Trust, 1967 January (Report 10365)
  - Meade, Edward. Evaluation of Evaluations: The Case of Follow-Through, 1968 March (Report 10366)
  - Meade, Edward. Instructional Media, 1967 November 15 (Report 10367)
  - Meade, Edward. Team Teaching Booklet, n.d. (Report 10368)
  - Newman, Brenda. Parent Education in the United States, 1972 September (Report 10369)
  - Porter, Douglas. Narrative Progress Report on Programmed Reading Research Project - #2, 1968 January (Report 10370)